<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
   
      <title>www.curiousgnu.com</title>
   
   <link>https://www.curiousgnu.com/</link>
   <description>Numbers, Graphs, and Apple Strudels</description>
   <language>en-uk</language>
   <managingEditor> CuriousGnu</managingEditor>
   <atom:link href="rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
   
	<item>
	  <title>Analyzing Subtitles - Chick Flick or Guy Movie?</title>
	  <link>//subtitles-target-audience</link>
	  <author>CuriousGnu</author>
	  <pubDate>2017-03-22T03:00:00+01:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//subtitles-target-audience</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>Romantic comedy or action movie? While this cliché certainly oversimplifies the differences in movie preferences between men and women, it is common knowledge that certain movie genres primarily target one gender. The colloquial term <em>chick flick</em> refers to movies targeted to a female audience whereas <em>guy movies</em> are mainly aimed at male viewers. For example, a study found that female viewers have a stronger preference for movies with happier themes than their male counterparts (<cite><a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1027/1864-1105.20.3.97">Banerjee et al., 2008</a></cite>).</p>

<p>For this post, my goal is to investigate how <em>chick flicks</em>, and <em>guy movies</em> differ regarding the words spoken. As obtaining the original scripts is rather difficult, I decided to analyze the movies’ subtitles instead, which were available from <cite><a href="https://www.amazon.com/s/?rh=n%3A7589478011%2Cn%3A2858905011%2Cp_n_consumption_type%3A9052272011%2Cp_n_feature_fourteen_browse-bin%3A2654454011%2Cp_n_ways_to_watch%3A12007867011%2Cp_n_feature_twelve_browse-bin%3A5824772011">Amazon Video</a></cite>. At the end of this post, you will find a brief description of how subtitles can be downloaded from the Amazon website. Since subtitles are protected by copyright, please understand that I cannot share the files that I used in this project.</p>

<h4 id="data">Data</h4>
<p>I downloaded the subtitles of the <strong>top 1,000</strong> <cite><a href="https://www.amazon.com/s/?rh=n%3A7589478011%2Cn%3A2858905011%2Cp_n_consumption_type%3A9052272011%2Cp_n_feature_fourteen_browse-bin%3A2654454011%2Cp_n_ways_to_watch%3A12007867011%2Cp_n_feature_twelve_browse-bin%3A5824772011">Amazon Video bestsellers</a></cite> (7th March, 2017) and gathered additional information from <cite><a href="https://www.imdb.com">IMDb</a></cite>. To determine whether a film is targeted at a male or female audience, I used the proportion of women votes on the IMDb score. In this sample, women make up on average about <strong>one-quarter</strong> of all gender votes.</p>

<p>25% of the movies with the lowest share of female votes were defined as <em>guy movies</em> while the top 25% were defined as <em>chick flicks</em>. Next, I removed movies with less than 1,000 total votes to ensure a fair comparison. Considering the rather vague definition of these two terms, I believe that this approach is sufficient for this context. The following table shows the top ten movies for each category:</p>

<table style="font-size:14px">
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>#</th>
      <th>Chick Flicks (% female votes)</th>
      <th>Guy Movies (% female votes)</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>1</td>
      <td>Never Back Down: No Surrender (3.8%)</td>
      <td>Northanger Abbey (81.7%)</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>2</td>
      <td>Justice League Dark (4.8%)</td>
      <td>Persuasion (72.3%)</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>3</td>
      <td>Dragon Ball Z: Resurrection (5.1%)</td>
      <td>The Last Song (65.4%)</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>4</td>
      <td>Batman: Bad Blood (5.2%)</td>
      <td>The Princess Diaries 2 (64.1%)</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>5</td>
      <td>Justice League: Throne of Atlantis (5.6%)</td>
      <td>Something Borrowed (62.6%)</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>6</td>
      <td>Kill Command (5.7%)</td>
      <td>Letters To Juliet (62.5%)</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>7</td>
      <td>Justice League vs. Teen Titans (6.3%)</td>
      <td>Ever After: A Cinderella Story (60.7%)</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>8</td>
      <td>Headshot (6.4%)</td>
      <td>Little Women (59.7%)</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>9</td>
      <td>We Were Soldiers (6.6%)</td>
      <td>27 Dresses (58.5%)</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>10</td>
      <td>Predator (6.7%)</td>
      <td>The Young Victoria (58.2%)</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h4 id="analysis">Analysis</h4>
<p>First, I used the ‘<cite><a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/wordcloud/"><em>wordcloud</em></a></cite>’ package in R to plot a comparison word cloud, which highlights the words that were heavily used in one of the two categories. To remove movie specific words, such as character names, I dropped all words from the sample that were not in at least three different movie subtitles.</p>

<p><a href="/assets/images/subtitles-target-audience/wordcloud.png"><img src="/assets/images/subtitles-target-audience/wordcloud.png" alt="Subtitles Wordcloud" style="max-width: 600px" /></a></p>

<p>The more frequent use of profane language in <em>guy movies</em> and the higher use of positive words in <em>chick flicks</em> is in line with the assumption that women prefer relationship movies while men are more interested in thriller and action genres. A quick sentiment analysis performed through the ‘<cite><a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/sentimentr/"><em>sentimentr</em></a></cite>’ R-package confirms that movies targeted at a female audience are slightly more positive than movies produced for a male audience.</p>

<p><a href="/assets/images/subtitles-target-audience/sentiment.png"><img src="/assets/images/subtitles-target-audience/sentiment.png" alt="Subtitles Sentiment" style="max-width: 500px" /></a></p>

<p>These results show that the use of certain words differs significantly between the two categories. Furthermore, these findings suggest that we can use subtitles to determine whether a movie is more likely to target a male or female audience. As this is a traditional text classification problem, a wide variety of machine learning algorithms exist, such as <cite><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Support_vector_machine">support vector machines</a></cite>, <cite><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Naive_Bayes_classifier">naive Bayes classifiers</a></cite>, or <cite><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boosting_(machine_learning)">boosting classifiers</a></cite>, which could be applied.</p>

<p>Even though some of these algorithms would probably be more accurate and robust for this task, I used a <cite><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Decision_tree_learning">classification tree</a></cite> model (‘<cite><a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/rpart/index.html"><em>rpart</em></a></cite>’, R-package) because it produces results that are easy to understand and apply. The goal of this method is to derive a set of rules from input variables that can predict which class an item belongs to. In this case, the input variables for each movie are the numbers of occurrences of each word stem. The target category is either <em>chick flick</em> or <em>guy movie</em>. The following tree is based on a randomly selected training set.</p>

<p><a href="/assets/images/subtitles-target-audience/tree.png"><img src="/assets/images/subtitles-target-audience/tree.png" alt="Subtitles Regression Tree" style="max-width: 500px" /></a></p>

<p>According to this model, if the word stem ‘<strong><em>love</em></strong>’ appears more than 11 times in the subtitles and ‘<strong><em>gun</em></strong>’ is only used once, the movie is most likely targeted at women. However, if ‘<strong><em>love</em></strong>’ occurs no more than 11 times in the subtitles and ‘<strong><em>hell</em></strong>’ at least once, the movie is probably produced for a male audience. When applied to the test set, this model predicts <strong>82%</strong> of the categories correctly. This is significantly higher than the <strong>54%</strong> no information rate, which is the percentage of the largest class in the training set.</p>

<p>Overall, I think it is quite interesting to see how the results support the assumption about typical <em>chick flicks</em> and <em>guy movies</em>. Knowing that gender specific movies are a controversial topic for some people, I hope that no one is offended by this post or my choice of words as this is unintentional.</p>

<h5 id="download-subtitles-from-amazon-video">Download Subtitles from Amazon Video</h5>
<p>Amazon Video offers high quality subtitles that can be downloaded in the <cite><a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/2006/CR-ttaf1-dfxp-20061116/"><em>DFXP format</em></a></cite> using Google Chrome’s Developer Tools. To get the subtitles, you need to start streaming the requested movie. Therefore, being a Prime member is very helpful as it includes free access to a large portion of the video content. Otherwise, gathering the subtitles for a large sample of movies could become rather expensive.</p>

<p><a href="/assets/images/subtitles-target-audience/screenshot.png"><img src="/assets/images/subtitles-target-audience/screenshot.png" alt="Subtitles Screenshot" style="max-width: 668px" /></a></p>

<ol>
  <li>Visit the movie’s product page (e.g. <cite><a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B01CUVU7DQ/">amazon.com/dp/B01CUVU7DQ</a></cite>)</li>
  <li>Open <em>Developer Tools</em></li>
  <li>Select the <em>Network</em> tab</li>
  <li>Click the <em>Watch Now</em> button</li>
  <li>Type ‘subtitle’ into the search bar</li>
  <li>Select <em>GetPlaybackResources?…</em> and open the <em>Preview</em> tab</li>
  <li>Open the URL under [subtitleURLs &gt; 0 &gt; url]</li>
  <li>Done!</li>
</ol>

<p>If you have any questions or concerns about this post, feel free to write me an <a href="&#109;&#097;&#105;&#108;&#116;&#111;:&#099;&#111;&#110;&#116;&#097;&#099;&#116;&#064;&#099;&#117;&#114;&#105;&#111;&#117;&#115;&#103;&#110;&#117;&#046;&#099;&#111;&#109;">email</a>.</p>


	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Age Differences of Celebrity Couples</title>
	  <link>//age-differences-celebrity-couples</link>
	  <author>CuriousGnu</author>
	  <pubDate>2017-01-26T13:00:00+01:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//age-differences-celebrity-couples</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>In one of my <a href="https://www.curiousgnu.com/imdb-age-gap">first posts</a>, I wrote about the age difference of movie couples and showed that the male is, on average, slightly older than his partner. The goal of this article is to find out whether there is a similar trend among real celebrity couples. Even though the age difference in sexual relationships is a frequent subject of proper scientific studies, I thought it would be still interesting to take a closer look at stars’ dating lives.</p>

<p>As a data source, I scraped the website <a href="http://www.whosdatedwho.com/">whosdatedwho.com</a> (WDW), which collects information about the dating history of celebrities. Since it is a typical gossip site, and also relies on rumors, it must be expected that some of the data is inaccurate or incomplete. Nevertheless, this should be acceptable for our use case. The web-scraping provided data on 53,820 celebrities (dataset: 2016/12/06). To ensure the relevance of the data, I only included relationships which started in the past 50 years in the sample where at least one partner had been among the 5,000 most searched celebrities (WDW Rank). In addition, I removed all relationships from the sample for which the birthdates of both partners were not available. After applying all the criteria, the sample consisted of 6,693 relationships.</p>

<p>While extracting the data from the HTML source was a straightforward process with the Python library, <a href="https://www.crummy.com/software/BeautifulSoup/">Beautiful Soup</a>, it was surprising that WDW doesn’t provide any information about gender. In cases where the sex couldn’t be derived from the occupation (e.g., actor/actresses), I used <a href="https://genderize.io/">genderize.io</a> to determine the gender from the first name and manually checked unclear cases.</p>

<p>To visualize the data, we can use a program like <a href="https://gephi.org/">Gephi</a> to plot the relationships as a network. For the following figure, I used Gephi’s ego network filter with a depth setting of 2 to illustrate to whom <em>Alexander Skarsgård</em>, a Swedish actor, was directly and indirectly connected.</p>

<p><a href="/assets/images/age-differences-celebrity-couples/net.png"><img src="/assets/images/age-differences-celebrity-couples/net.png" alt="Whosdatedwho.com Network" style="max-width:500px" /></a></p>

<p>This figure indicates that both <em>Alexander Skarsgård</em> and <em>Marilyn Manson</em>, an American singer, dated the actress <em>Evan Rachel Wood</em>. Next, let’s look at the ages of the partners at the start of their (alleged) relationships. The 2D density plot shows the age of the male partner on the x-axis and the age of the female partner on the y-axis. The plot suggests that, in many cases, the man is slightly older than his female partner, a difference that gets bigger with the increasing age of the male. Overall, this age disparity is similar to the age difference among married couples in Western countries (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Age_disparity_in_sexual_relationships">Wikipedia</a>).</p>

<p><a href="/assets/images/age-differences-celebrity-couples/density.png"><img src="/assets/images/age-differences-celebrity-couples/density.png" alt="Couples - Density Plot" style="max-width:500px" /></a></p>

<p>To visualize the age difference across certain age groups, I used the R package <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/yarrr/index.html">yarrr</a> for the next pirate plot. The plot illustrates that the age disparity in new relationships increases significantly when male celebrities get older. While male stars in their <strong>20s</strong> have female partners  <strong>2.4 years</strong> older on average, the women in new relationships with <strong>40- to 49-year-olds</strong> and <strong>over-50s</strong> are about <strong>6.0</strong> and <strong>16.5 years younger</strong>, respectively.</p>

<style type="text/css">
	.tg-ba  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;border:none;max-width: 400px;border-top: 2px #333 solid;border-bottom: 2px #333 solid;}
	.tg-ba td{font-size:14px;padding:1px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:0px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;background-color:#fff!important;text-align:center}
	.tg-ba th{font-size:14px;font-weight:normal;padding:1px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:0px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;background-color:#fff!important;text-align:center;border-bottom: 1px #333 solid;}
	.tg-ba .tg-c9cr{font-style:italic}
	.tg-ba .tg-wxgh{text-decoration:underline;vertical-align:top}
	.tg-ba .tg-yw4l{vertical-align:top}
	.tg-ba .tg-db0a{text-decoration:underline}
</style>

<center>
	<table class="tg-ba">
		<tr>
			<th class="tg-031e"></th>
			<th class="tg-c9cr" colspan="2">age difference</th>
			<th class="tg-yw4l"></th>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tg-db0a">age (male)</td>
			<td class="tg-db0a">mean</td>
			<td class="tg-wxgh">median</td>
			<td class="tg-wxgh">n</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tg-031e">20-29</td>
			<td class="tg-031e">-2.39</td>
			<td class="tg-yw4l">-1</td>
			<td class="tg-yw4l">420</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tg-031e">30-39</td>
			<td class="tg-031e">0.51</td>
			<td class="tg-yw4l">1</td>
			<td class="tg-yw4l">3,170</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tg-031e">40-49</td>
			<td class="tg-031e">5.99</td>
			<td class="tg-yw4l">7</td>
			<td class="tg-yw4l">2,130</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="tg-031e">50+</td>
			<td class="tg-031e">16.47</td>
			<td class="tg-yw4l">17</td>
			<td class="tg-yw4l">973</td>
		</tr>
	</table>
</center>

<p><a href="/assets/images/age-differences-celebrity-couples/pirate.png"><img src="/assets/images/age-differences-celebrity-couples/pirate.png" alt="Couples - Pirate Plot" style="max-width:500px" /></a></p>

<p>A regression analysis can be applied to examine the relationship between female and male age further. To automatically account for non-linearity, I chose <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Multivariate_adaptive_regression_splines">MARS</a> (<a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/earth/index.html">earth</a> R package). The result shows the age difference changes with the increasing age of the male partner. The shaded area is the 90% prediction interval. According to the model, the new partner (female) of a <strong>40-year-old</strong> male celebrity who started dating is on average <strong>9.8 years younger</strong>.</p>

<p><a href="/assets/images/age-differences-celebrity-couples/regression.png"><img src="/assets/images/age-differences-celebrity-couples/regression.png" alt="Couples - Pirate Regression" style="max-width:600px" /></a></p>

<p>Overall, the data shows that the often criticized age difference among movie couples may not be too far from reality, or at least the reality of some celebrities. If you have questions or concerns, feel free to write me an <a href="&#109;&#097;&#105;&#108;&#116;&#111;:&#099;&#111;&#110;&#116;&#097;&#099;&#116;&#064;&#099;&#117;&#114;&#105;&#111;&#117;&#115;&#103;&#110;&#117;&#046;&#099;&#111;&#109;">email</a>.</p>


	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Using Amazon's X-Ray to Visualize Characters' Screen Time</title>
	  <link>//movie-character-screen-time</link>
	  <author>CuriousGnu</author>
	  <pubDate>2016-06-22T03:00:00+02:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//movie-character-screen-time</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>Today’s blog post is once again about the visualization of movie data. As I already experimented with the IMDb dataset to <a href="http://www.curiousgnu.com/imdb-age-gap">compare the average age</a> of actors and actresses, I wanted to try something a bit different. One thing that I have always found cool is the visualization of movie plots (e.g. <a href="https://xkcd.com/657/">xkcd</a>). The reason why I never attempted to do something like this myself was that I had no idea from where I could get the required data. Of course, there is always the possibility to generate the data manually, but that is usually a tedious task that I try to avoid. Fortunately, I found a much more convenient data source, while I was watching a movie on the <a href="https://www.amazon.com/video">Amazon Video</a> app.</p>

<p><a href="/assets/images/movie-character-screen-time/xray_screenshot.jpg"><img src="/assets/images/movie-character-screen-time/xray_screenshot.jpg" alt="X-Ray Screenshot" style="max-width: 480px" /></a></p>

<p>Its X-Ray feature shows you relevant IMDb information based on which actor is currently in the scene. The app does that based on a single text file which contains the information for when a character appears in a scene. At the end of the post, I will describe how you can extract the file yourself. First, I downloaded the X-Ray file for the latest <a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B019G7X9E6">Star Wars movie</a>. Based on this data we can compare the characters by their screen time.</p>

<p><a href="/assets/images/movie-character-screen-time/barplot.png"><img src="/assets/images/movie-character-screen-time/barplot.png" alt="Characters Screen Time by Minutes" style="max-width: 647px" /></a></p>

<p>I noticed that the numbers are not always 100% accurate because some characters are only visible in parts of a scene. However, it should not be a major problem for which we are using them in this post. Next, I used the <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/ggplot2/"><em>ggplot2</em></a> package in R to plot the following Gantt chart:</p>

<p><a href="/assets/images/movie-character-screen-time/tp_starwars.png"><img src="/assets/images/movie-character-screen-time/tp_starwars.png" alt="Star Wars The Force Awakens" /></a></p>

<p>We can use the X-Ray data, not only to identify in which scene a character appears but also with whom else. To visualize this information, I used <a href="https://gephi.org/"><em>Gephi</em></a>, an open source tool to plot networks. My assumption is that the longer characters appear on-screen together, the closer their relationship is. The circle size is based on their total screen time.</p>

<p><a href="/assets/images/movie-character-screen-time/network.png"><img src="/assets/images/movie-character-screen-time/network.png" alt="Star Wars - Network Plot" style="max-width: 512px" /></a></p>

<p>I hope these examples show what you can do with Amazon X-Ray data relatively quickly. The best thing of this approach is that it only requires a minimum manual work. So, here are Gantt charts for three other movies I enjoy:
<a href="/assets/images/movie-character-screen-time/tp_big_lebowski.png"><img src="/assets/images/movie-character-screen-time/tp_big_lebowski.png" alt="The Big Lebowski" /></a></p>

<p><a href="/assets/images/movie-character-screen-time/tp_pulp_fiction.png"><img src="/assets/images/movie-character-screen-time/tp_pulp_fiction.png" alt="Pulp Fiction" /></a></p>

<p><a href="/assets/images/movie-character-screen-time/tp_john_wick.png"><img src="/assets/images/movie-character-screen-time/tp_john_wick.png" alt="John Wick" /></a></p>

<h4 id="how-to-get-x-ray-data">How to Get X-Ray Data?</h4>

<p>The X-Ray feature is based on an unencrypted JSON file which can be downloaded with the Chrome browser. Unfortunately, those files are not publicly available (signed CloudFront URL), meaning that you have to start streaming the movie before you can download the file. This also means that you are limited to the content included in your Prime subscription, or you need to rent/buy the movies in which you are interested. Nevertheless, I think it is still an interesting source, especially when you consider the alternatives.</p>

<ol>
  <li>Start Developer Tools: Menu &gt; Tools &gt; Developer Tools</li>
  <li>Start streaming a video &amp; close the player after a few seconds</li>
  <li>Select the following Developer Tools settings:</li>
</ol>

<p><a href="/assets/images/movie-character-screen-time/devtools.png"><img src="/assets/images/movie-character-screen-time/devtools.png" alt="DevTools Settings" /></a></p>

<ol>
  <li>Click on the gray record button to capture the network traffic</li>
  <li>Start streaming the video again</li>
  <li>Now the following file should appear: <em>data.json?Expires=</em></li>
  <li>Right-click on the file &gt; Open Link in New Tab &gt; Save Page As…</li>
</ol>

<p>Then you can use in R the <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/jsonlite/index.html"><em>jsonlite</em></a> package to load the JSON file and then do, for example, something like this:</p>

<pre><code>library(jsonlite)
library(ggplot2)

data &lt;- fromJSON("starwars.json", flatten = TRUE)
e &lt;- data$resource$events
e$start &lt;- as.numeric(as.data.frame(e$when)[1,])
e$end &lt;- as.numeric(as.data.frame(e$when)[2,])
ggplot(e, aes(colour=e$character)) + 
  geom_segment(aes(x=e$start, xend=e$end, y=e$character, yend=e$character), size=5)
</code></pre>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>What's the age difference in movies?</title>
	  <link>//imdb-age-gap</link>
	  <author>CuriousGnu</author>
	  <pubDate>2015-11-04T13:21:00+01:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//imdb-age-gap</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>In response to my <a href="/imdb-age-distribution">last post</a> about the distribution of ages of actresses and actors, a Reddit user suggested investigating further the age difference between female and male movie stars. In my first simple analysis, I only compared the average ages of both groups in the overall sample. Now, the next step is to check on a movie basis if there is an age difference between the leading actress and her co-star.</p>

<h5 id="methods">Methods</h5>
<p>First I needed to identify the two leads of each film (2000-2015, with 10,000+ votes) to calculate the age difference. Unfortunately, there is no direct way to get this information from the IMDb dataset. I, therefore, used a quick-and-dirty approve and chose the first actress and actor in the IMDb cast credits as leads. If I did not find both an actress and an actor in the first three entries (in credits order), I removed the whole movie from the sample. With this method, I was able to get the leading actresses and actors of 1,201 movies. Note that they are not necessarily movie couples. I am aware that a manually selected sample would have been better but considering the simplicity of my approach; I think that the results are acceptable for this analysis. Feel free to check it yourself <a href="/assets/data/age_gap_2015.csv">here</a>.</p>

<h5 id="results">Results</h5>
<p>When we look at the box-plot of the age differences, we can see that on average the leading actor is <strong>five years older</strong> than his female co-star. It also tells us that in approximately 75% of all movies in our sample have an older male lead. Based on this data, the answer to the question from the title is <em>“Yes”</em> even though the age gap might be not as big as expected.</p>

<p><a href="/assets/images/age-gap/plot_2.png"><img src="/assets/images/age-gap/plot_2.png" alt="Age Gap Boxplot" title="Age Gap Boxplot" /></a></p>

<p>Finally, I also created a density plot which summarizes all data points in a nice looking, colorful graph. The area below the gray dashed line stands for all the movies in which the leading actor is older :</p>

<p><a href="/assets/images/age-gap/plot_1_hd.png"><img src="/assets/images/age-gap/plot_1.png" alt="Age Gap Plot" title="Age Gap Plot" /></a></p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Actresses Are on Average 7 Years Younger</title>
	  <link>//imdb-age-distribution</link>
	  <author>CuriousGnu</author>
	  <pubDate>2015-11-02T21:10:00+01:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//imdb-age-distribution</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>The IMDb dataset is a great source for everyone loves movies and numbers. After I had figured out how to <a href="http://imdbpy.sourceforge.net/support.html" target="_blank">import the data</a> into a local SQL database, the first thing I did was to look at the age of the actresses and actors during filming.</p>

<p>It turns out that the average actress is, with a median age of 32, <strong>seven years younger</strong> than her male counterpart who is on average 39 years old. The diagram below shows that the distribution of ages of actresses is more skewed to the right (γ1=.912) than those of ages of actors (γ1=.483). This suggests that there is a relatively higher demand for actresses under the age of 35. Interestingly we do not see such an apparent age preference in the casting of actors.</p>

<p><a href="/assets/images/age-dist/plot_hd.png"><img src="/assets/images/age-dist/plot.png" alt="Age Distribution Plot" title="Age Distribution Plot" /></a></p>

<p>The sample consists of all roles played by actresses (n=21,551) and actors (n=50,165) in U.S. movie released between 2000 and 2015, with more than 10,000 IMDb-Votes. By the way, in the United States, the median age of females and males is 39.2 years and 36.5 years respectively (<a href="https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/us.html">The World Factbook, 2015</a>).</p>

<p><small>Photo: “California Movie Theater Berkeley” by <a href="https://flic.kr/p/aM4GwX">Russell Mondy</a> is licensed under CC BY-NC 2.0</small></p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>


</channel>
</rss>
