<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
   
      <title>www.curiousgnu.com</title>
   
   <link>https://www.curiousgnu.com/</link>
   <description>Numbers, Graphs, and Apple Strudels</description>
   <language>en-uk</language>
   <managingEditor> CuriousGnu</managingEditor>
   <atom:link href="rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
   
	<item>
	  <title>Chicago pays female employees only 80% of what it pays male employees</title>
	  <link>//pay-gap</link>
	  <author>CuriousGnu</author>
	  <pubDate>2016-07-05T03:00:00+02:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//pay-gap</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>While I was browsing through the City of <a href="https://data.cityofchicago.org/">Chicago’s Data Catalog</a>, I came across a <a href="https://data.cityofchicago.org/Administration-Finance/Current-Employee-Names-Salaries-and-Position-Title/xzkq-xp2w">dataset</a> of the city’s 32,000 employees which included their full names, position titles, and annual salaries. I thought that it was a great opportunity to find out whether the gender pay gap was a problem there also. The gender pay gap is the average difference between men’s and women’s earnings, which in the US is somewhere around <a href="http://www.iwpr.org/initiatives/pay-equity-and-discrimination">-21%</a> for women. It is an important number many politicians and activists use as proof for gender inequality.</p>

<p>Before I could compare the average salaries of female and male city employees, I needed to identify their gender – a piece of information which was not included in the official dataset. To do this, I used the R-Package <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/gender/index.html"><em>gender</em></a> to predict the gender of a person based on his or her first name. Of course, this method isn’t 100% accurate, but because of the high number of employees, this potential inaccuracy shouldn’t be a problem. After that, I was able to compare the average annual salaries of male and female city employees. It turns out that the City of Chicago isn’t any better than the rest of the nation. It pays its female employees on average, only 80% of what their male colleagues make – which is very close to the national average of 79%.</p>

<p><a href="/assets/images/pay-gap/barchart.png"><img src="/assets/images/pay-gap/barchart.png" alt="Pay Gap Barchart" style="max-width: 500px" /></a></p>

<p>If you think now that there are many other factors besides gender, that determine a person’s salary, and that chart above is completely useless, you are right. It’s obviously not good enough to compare only the average earnings of both genders if they do different kinds of jobs. The criticism of how the gender pay gap is used in political discussions isn’t something new, and it has been proven many times that the gender pay gap isn’t a sufficient proof for gender inequality.</p>

<p>I think one of the problems with the arguments against the gender pay gap is that they often rely on statistical tests. Don’t get me wrong, these tests are the only scientifically correct way to do it; but unfortunately, many people stop listening to you as soon as you start mentioning t-tests and confidence levels. The reason why I find the Chicago dataset so interesting is that it contains the salaries of each employee, which allows us to use it as a real-world example to illustrate the problems with the gender pay gap argument. To do this, I propose a simple scatter plot to display the average male and female salaries per position title.</p>

<p><a href="/assets/images/pay-gap/sketch.png"><img src="/assets/images/pay-gap/sketch.png" alt="Pay Gap Sketch" style="max-width: 300px" /></a></p>

<p>So, each dot represents one job position, like police officer or police sergeant. If a dot (1) is below the 45-degree line, the average salary of men is higher than the average salary of women holding the same position. If a dot (2) is above the 45-degree line, it’s the other way around. In case the average salaries of both genders are equal, the dot (3) sits directly on the line. Based on this idea, I generated the following plot:</p>

<p><a href="/assets/images/pay-gap/scatter_plot.png"><img src="/assets/images/pay-gap/scatter_plot.png" alt="Pay Gap Scatter Plot" style="max-width: 600px" /></a></p>

<p>This plot clearly shows that women are not systematically paid 20% less for doing the same job as the first bar chart might have suggested.  The main reason for the difference is that women are doing different jobs than men do. Therefore, the gender pay gap shouldn’t be used as an argument for the existence of gender inequality but gender differences. I’m not saying that gender discrimination doesn’t exist in the workplace, it’s just that the gender pay gap doesn’t support the claim that women are paid 20% less for doing the same job. Therefore, a more honest way to use this statistic would be in a discussion about how both gender and personal choices affect careers.</p>

<p>In conclusion, it’s true that the gender pay gap exists, and that on average, women make less money than men. However, the claims that it proves gender inequality are false because women are simply doing different kinds of jobs.</p>

<p>If you have questions or concerns, feel free to write me an  <a href="&#109;&#097;&#105;&#108;&#116;&#111;:&#099;&#111;&#110;&#116;&#097;&#099;&#116;&#064;&#099;&#117;&#114;&#105;&#111;&#117;&#115;&#103;&#110;&#117;&#046;&#099;&#111;&#109;">email</a>.</p>

<p><small>Photo: “Chicago” by <a href="https://flic.kr/p/62vAsR">Tony Webster</a> is licensed under CC BY 2.0</small></p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>How The World Sees Hillary Clinton & Donald Trump</title>
	  <link>//how-the-world-sees-clinton-trump</link>
	  <author>CuriousGnu</author>
	  <pubDate>2016-04-27T19:14:00+02:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//how-the-world-sees-clinton-trump</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>For this week’s blog post, I will try to find out how the international news media writes about Hillary Clinton and Donald Trump; the presidential front-runners of both parties. The plan is to check on several international news sources to derive positive and negative things regarding Hillary Clinton or Donald Trump. Doing this will give us an idea of how the news media in other countries, writes and talks about the two candidates.</p>

<p>Fortunately, most of the hard work was already done by the <a href="http://gdeltproject.org/">GDELT Project</a>, which monitors news sites from all around the world and makes its work freely available for everyone. They even automatically determine how positive or negative news articles are using sentiment analysis. Based on the <a href="http://gdeltproject.org/data.html">GDELT dataset</a>, I created a map for each candidate which shows how the average tone of the texts compares to American news (Clinton: -1.15; Trump: -1.40). The results are based on a total of over <strong>550,000 articles</strong> published after July 2015 of which 65.3% mentioned <em>Donald Trump</em> at least twice, and 46.1% mentioned <em>Hillary Clinton</em> at least twice.</p>

<div class="emb-iframe">
  <iframe height="612" width="980" frameborder="0" src="https://curiousgnu.cartodb.com/viz/5497e1dc-0991-11e6-87dd-0e5db1731f59/embed_map" allowfullscreen="" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" oallowfullscreen="" msallowfullscreen=""></iframe>
</div>
<div class="emb-iframe">
  <iframe height="612" width="980" frameborder="0" src="https://curiousgnu.cartodb.com/viz/676de180-0991-11e6-9940-0e674067d321/embed_map" allowfullscreen="" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" oallowfullscreen="" msallowfullscreen=""></iframe>
</div>

<p>Compared to the Republican front-runner Donald Trump, international journalists seem to view Hillary Clinton much more positively. Looking at the maps above, we can see that news articles from countries like <em>Mexico</em>, <em>India</em>, or <em>China</em> are clearly more favorable towards Clinton than Trump. One exception is the Russian media which reports 19% more positively about Trump than its American counterpart. I don’t want to get political, but I think the results for some countries aren’t much of a surprise.</p>

<h4 id="technical-background">Technical Background</h4>

<p>The process of doing this analysis is fairly straightforward and does not require anything except a browser and a Google account. First, I used the <a href="http://gdeltproject.org/">GDELT database</a>, publicly available on <a href="https://bigquery.cloud.google.com/table/gdelt-bq:gdeltv2.gkg">Google BigQuery</a>, to extract the raw data needed to create both maps. I wrote the following SQL query to do this:</p>

<pre class="sql"><code>SELECT	a.country
	,AVG(CASE WHEN a.trump = 1 
		THEN a.tone ELSE NULL END) trump_tone
	,AVG(CASE WHEN a.hillary = 1
		THEN a.tone ELSE NULL END) hillary_tone
FROM (SELECT 
  cc.CountryHumanName country
  ,CASE WHEN 
  	LOWER(gkg.AllNames) LIKE '%donald%trump%donald%trump%'
  	THEN 1 ELSE 0 END trump
  ,CASE WHEN
  	LOWER(gkg.AllNames) LIKE '%hillary%clinton%hillary%clinton%'
  	THEN 1 ELSE 0 END hillary
  ,FIRST(SPLIT(gkg.V2Tone, ',')) tone
FROM [gdelt-bq:gdeltv2.gkg] gkg
INNER JOIN [gdelt-bq:gdeltv2.domainsbycountry_alllangs_april2015] cc
  ON cc.Domain = gkg.SourceCommonName
WHERE (
  	LOWER(gkg.AllNames) LIKE '%donald%trump%donald%trump%'
  	OR LOWER(gkg.AllNames) LIKE '%hillary%clinton%hillary%clinton%'
  ) AND gkg.DATE &gt;= 20150801000000
) a
GROUP BY a.country
HAVING	SUM(a.trump) &gt;= 100
	AND SUM(a.hillary) &gt;= 100
</code></pre>

<p>In the second step, I exported the results of the query as a CSV file and uploaded it to <a href="https://cartodb.com/">CartoDB</a>, a free web service where you can create maps based on location-based data. From there on you can follow their documentation and have your maps ready in no time.</p>

<p>From my experience, <a href="https://cartodb.com/">CartoDB</a> is a great tool if you want to create interactive and highly customizable maps. If you only need a basic set of features, you ought to try out <a href="https://www.google.com/sheets/about/">Google Sheets</a>. <a href="http://www.tableau.com/">Tableau</a> is another good alternative that I frequently use, which is also available in the free version <a href="https://public.tableau.com/s/">Tableau Public</a>. I didn’t use Tableau in this project because CartoDB offers much better embedding options for blogs or websites.</p>

<p>If you have any questions about this blog post, feel free to contact me by <a href="&#109;&#097;&#105;&#108;&#116;&#111;:&#099;&#111;&#110;&#116;&#097;&#099;&#116;&#064;&#099;&#117;&#114;&#105;&#111;&#117;&#115;&#103;&#110;&#117;&#046;&#099;&#111;&#109;">email</a> or write me a PM on Reddit.</p>

<p> </p>

<p><small>Photos by <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/gageskidmore/">Gage Skidmore</a> is licensed under CC BY-SA 2.0</small></p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>


</channel>
</rss>
