<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
   
      <title>www.curiousgnu.com</title>
   
   <link>http://www.curiousgnu.com/</link>
   <description>Numbers, Graphs, and Apple Strudels</description>
   <language>en-uk</language>
   <managingEditor> CuriousGnu</managingEditor>
   <atom:link href="rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
   
	<item>
	  <title>How The World Sees Hillary Clinton & Donald Trump</title>
	  <link>//how-the-world-sees-clinton-trump</link>
	  <author>CuriousGnu</author>
	  <pubDate>2016-04-26T20:14:00+02:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//how-the-world-sees-clinton-trump</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>For this week’s blog post, I will try to find out how the international news media writes about Hillary Clinton and Donald Trump; the presidential front-runners of both parties. The plan is to check on several international news sources to derive positive and negative things regarding Hillary Clinton or Donald Trump. Doing this will give us an idea of how the news media in other countries, writes and talks about the two candidates.</p>

<p>Fortunately, most of the hard work was already done by the <a href="http://gdeltproject.org/">GDELT Project</a>, which monitors news sites from all around the world and makes its work freely available for everyone. They even automatically determine how positive or negative news articles are using sentiment analysis. Based on the <a href="http://gdeltproject.org/data.html">GDELT dataset</a>, I created a map for each candidate which shows how the average tone of the texts compares to American news (Clinton: -1.15; Trump: -1.40). The results are based on a total of over <strong>550,000 articles</strong> published after July 2015 of which 65.3% mentioned <em>Donald Trump</em> at least twice, and 46.1% mentioned <em>Hillary Clinton</em> at least twice.</p>

<div class="emb-iframe">
  <iframe height="612" width="980" frameborder="0" src="https://curiousgnu.cartodb.com/viz/5497e1dc-0991-11e6-87dd-0e5db1731f59/embed_map" allowfullscreen="" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" oallowfullscreen="" msallowfullscreen=""></iframe>
</div>
<div class="emb-iframe">
  <iframe height="612" width="980" frameborder="0" src="https://curiousgnu.cartodb.com/viz/676de180-0991-11e6-9940-0e674067d321/embed_map" allowfullscreen="" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" oallowfullscreen="" msallowfullscreen=""></iframe>
</div>

<p>Compared to the Republican front-runner Donald Trump, international journalists seem to view Hillary Clinton much more positively. Looking at the maps above, we can see that news articles from countries like <em>Mexico</em>, <em>India</em>, or <em>China</em> are clearly more favorable towards Clinton than Trump. One exception is the Russian media which reports 19% more positively about Trump than its American counterpart. I don’t want to get political, but I think the results for some countries aren’t much of a surprise.</p>

<h4 id="technical-background">Technical Background</h4>

<p>The process of doing this analysis is fairly straightforward and does not require anything except a browser and a Google account. First, I used the <a href="http://gdeltproject.org/">GDELT database</a>, publicly available on <a href="https://bigquery.cloud.google.com/table/gdelt-bq:gdeltv2.gkg">Google BigQuery</a>, to extract the raw data needed to create both maps. I wrote the following SQL query to do this:</p>

<pre class="sql"><code>SELECT	a.country
	,AVG(CASE WHEN a.trump = 1 
		THEN a.tone ELSE NULL END) trump_tone
	,AVG(CASE WHEN a.hillary = 1
		THEN a.tone ELSE NULL END) hillary_tone
FROM (SELECT 
  cc.CountryHumanName country
  ,CASE WHEN 
  	LOWER(gkg.AllNames) LIKE '%donald%trump%donald%trump%'
  	THEN 1 ELSE 0 END trump
  ,CASE WHEN
  	LOWER(gkg.AllNames) LIKE '%hillary%clinton%hillary%clinton%'
  	THEN 1 ELSE 0 END hillary
  ,FIRST(SPLIT(gkg.V2Tone, ',')) tone
FROM [gdelt-bq:gdeltv2.gkg] gkg
INNER JOIN [gdelt-bq:gdeltv2.domainsbycountry_alllangs_april2015] cc
  ON cc.Domain = gkg.SourceCommonName
WHERE (
  	LOWER(gkg.AllNames) LIKE '%donald%trump%donald%trump%'
  	OR LOWER(gkg.AllNames) LIKE '%hillary%clinton%hillary%clinton%'
  ) AND gkg.DATE &gt;= 20150801000000
) a
GROUP BY a.country
HAVING	SUM(a.trump) &gt;= 100
	AND SUM(a.hillary) &gt;= 100
</code></pre>

<p>In the second step, I exported the results of the query as a CSV file and uploaded it to <a href="https://cartodb.com/">CartoDB</a>, a free web service where you can create maps based on location-based data. From there on you can follow their documentation and have your maps ready in no time.</p>

<p>From my experience, <a href="https://cartodb.com/">CartoDB</a> is a great tool if you want to create interactive and highly customizable maps. If you only need a basic set of features, you ought to try out <a href="https://www.google.com/sheets/about/">Google Sheets</a>. <a href="http://www.tableau.com/">Tableau</a> is another good alternative that I frequently use, which is also available in the free version <a href="https://public.tableau.com/s/">Tableau Public</a>. I didn’t use Tableau in this project because CartoDB offers much better embedding options for blogs or websites.</p>

<p>If you have any questions about this blog post, feel free to contact me by <a href="&#109;&#097;&#105;&#108;&#116;&#111;:&#099;&#111;&#110;&#116;&#097;&#099;&#116;&#064;&#099;&#117;&#114;&#105;&#111;&#117;&#115;&#103;&#110;&#117;&#046;&#099;&#111;&#109;">email</a> or write me a PM on Reddit.</p>

<p> </p>

<p><small>Photos by <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/gageskidmore/">Gage Skidmore</a> is licensed under CC BY-SA 2.0</small></p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Redditors who commented in /r/X also commented in /r/Y</title>
	  <link>//reddit-comments</link>
	  <author>CuriousGnu</author>
	  <pubDate>2016-04-20T14:14:00+02:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//reddit-comments</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>This blog article is about <a href="http://www.reddit.com">reddit.com</a>, a website where people can post links to interesting websites and discuss a wide variety of different topics. According to <a href="http://www.alexa.com/topsites/countries/US">Alexa</a>, a company who analyzes web traffic, Reddit is the ninth most popular site in the United States. Reddit has thousands of different subcategories, called subreddits, which are usually moderated by volunteers. There are subreddits for nearly every topic you can imagine; for example, on <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/movies">/r/movies</a> people can discuss the latest blockbuster whereas the users over at <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/sloths">/r/sloths</a> are passionately committed to collecting cute pictures of sloths.</p>

<p>But Reddit can also be fascinating to people who are interested in data research because the user generated data is easily accessible via the official API and through <a href="https://bigquery.cloud.google.com/table/fh-bigquery:reddit_comments.2016_01">Google BigQuery</a> where you can find an SQL database which you can use for little to no cost. For this article, I decided to start with something simple. My goal is to find out how the 50 most popular subreddits are related to each other. The idea behind it is that users usually write comments in subreddits which are close to their personal interests, meaning that a user who is active in the <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/StarWars">/r/StarWars</a> subreddit is probably also active in the <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/firefly">/r/firefly</a> subreddit because both categories fit his or her interest in science fiction.</p>

<p><a href="/assets/images/rd-comments/rd_comments_net_hd.png"><img src="/assets/images/rd-comments/rd_comments_net_hd.png" alt="Subreddit Network" style="max-height:640px; max-width:640px" /></a></p>

<p>Based on this assumption, my approach was to look at all 1.2 million unique users who posted a comment in at least one of the top 50 subreddits during January 2016. To calculate the strength of the relationship between the subreddits, I used multiple logistic regression models which for example can tell us how much the probability of a Redditor posting a comment in <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/StarWars">/r/StarWars</a> increases if he or she also posted a comment in <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/firefly">/r/firefly</a>. The bigger this number is, the more closely related those subreddits are to each other. The network graph above is a visualization of these results. A bigger dot stands for a larger number of connections to its neighbors.</p>

<p>Looking at the graph, we can identify four major groups of subreddits:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>News &amp; Science</strong>: <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/worldnews">/r/worldnews</a>, <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/science">/r/science</a>, <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/space">/r/space</a>, <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/futurology">/r/futurology</a>, …</li>
  <li><strong>Entertainment</strong>: <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/movies">/r/movies</a>, <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/television">/r/television</a>, <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/music">/r/music</a>, <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/books">/r/books</a>, …</li>
  <li><strong>Visual Content</strong>: <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/funny">/r/funny</a>, <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/pics">/r/pics</a>, <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/aww">/r/aww</a>, <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/creepy">/r/creepy</a>, …</li>
  <li><strong>Textual Content</strong>: <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/showerthought">/r/showerthought</a>, <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/askreddit">/r/askreddit</a>, <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/tifu">/r/tifu</a>, <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/lifeprotips">/r/lifeprotips</a>, …</li>
</ol>

<p>The subreddit <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/todayilearned">/r/todayilearned</a> doesn’t belong to any particular group because it’s somewhat popular among all users. This analysis doesn’t go into great detail, but I think it’s nevertheless interesting to see that the groups of subreddit seem to make sense and can be interpreted. For example, it doesn’t sound wrong that users who enjoy commenting on topics about space are also interested in science.</p>

<p>Additionally, I also made a table from the same data. The software programs I used to create both graphs are <a href="https://gephi.org/">Gephi</a> and <a href="https://public.tableau.com/s/">Tableau</a> respectively. A blue square stands for a positive correlation coefficient whereas a red square represents the opposite.  You can open the full table by clicking on the graph below:</p>

<p><a href="https://public.tableau.com/profile/curious.gnu#!/vizhome/RedditComments-LogitRegressioncuriousgnu_com/Sheet1"><img src="/assets/images/rd-comments/rd_table.png" alt="Subreddit Table" /></a></p>

<p>Admittedly, these aren’t exactly groundbreaking results, but it was real fun to try out some statistical methods on this huge amount of data. I’m currently testing how I can use this data source for an article about text analysis.</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>


</channel>
</rss>
