<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
   
      <title>www.curiousgnu.com</title>
   
   <link>https://www.curiousgnu.com/</link>
   <description>Numbers, Graphs, and Apple Strudels</description>
   <language>en-uk</language>
   <managingEditor> CuriousGnu</managingEditor>
   <atom:link href="rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
   
	<item>
	  <title>A Darknet Site Currently Offers 42,497 U.S. Credit Cards</title>
	  <link>//darknet-credit-cards</link>
	  <author>CuriousGnu</author>
	  <pubDate>2016-09-06T03:00:00+02:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//darknet-credit-cards</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>Last week, I found out that my credit card information was stolen and used by criminals for an expensive shopping spree. This incident inspired me to revisit my <a href="https://www.curiousgnu.com/cryptomarkets-lsd-sales">previous post</a> about drug dealing on the Darknet and research how stolen credit cards are traded there. I was able to gather a dataset of <strong>42,497</strong> stolen U.S. credit cards which are currently sold on a Darknet site. At the end of this post, you’ll find a link to a site that allows you to see if your card is in this dataset.</p>

<p>The Darknet, a part of the internet which is only accessible with special software like the <a href="https://www.torproject.org/projects/torbrowser.html.en">Tor Browser</a>, allows users and website owners to stay anonymous. The anonymity not only makes the Darknet an essential tool for people like reporters or activists, but is also used widely by criminals. Nowadays the Darknet hosts multiple <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Darknet_market">Cryptomarkets</a>, which are marketplaces similar to eBay where vendors can sell products like illicit drugs, counterfeit money, or stolen credit cards. I decided to take a close look at the AlphaBay Market because it’s one of the largest marketplaces and relatively easy to scrape.</p>

<p><a href="/assets/images/darknet-credit-cards/alphabay_screenshot.png"><img src="/assets/images/darknet-credit-cards/alphabay_screenshot.png" alt="AlphaBay - Screenshot" style="max-width: 600px" /></a></p>

<p>The AlphaBay Market has a feature called <em>CC Autoshop</em> that allows potential buyers to search a database of all the stolen credit cards that are offered by different sellers. For example, it’s possible to only search for cards from a particular city. That’s important for criminals who try to circumvent anti-fraud measures by using stolen cards from the same region or state in which they are located. But it also means that the sellers have to reveal information that we can analyze.</p>

<p>First, I downloaded the entire <em>CC Autoshop</em> as HTML files before I used the Python library <em>Beautiful Soup</em> to extract the information. I got 42,497 U.S. credit cards which were offered on September 1st, 2016 as a result. The total value of is <strong>$324,941</strong> with an average price of <strong>$7.65 per card</strong>. Some cards (1025) even include the Social Security number of the owner. Considering that nearly 13 million Americans are victims of identity fraud each year, this number almost seems insignificant, but it can nevertheless cause millions of dollars in damages. What I find particularly concerning is that anyone can purchase these cards after doing basic internet research.</p>

<p><a href="/assets/images/darknet-credit-cards/map.jpg"><img src="/assets/images/darknet-credit-cards/map.jpg" alt="AlphaBay - Countries" /></a></p>

<p>The map above shows how many cards from each state are offered on the AlphaBay Market. It is suprising that <strong>27%</strong> (11,338) of them are from Delaware and are sold by only two major sellers (<em>Sasha_Grey</em> and <em>HotPizza</em>). Unfortunately, I can only speculate about the reasons for this. Are those just company credit cards or does it suggest a local card breach? The following graph is an overview of all active AlphaBay CC vendors based on the total number of cards they offer.</p>

<p><a href="/assets/images/darknet-credit-cards/treemap.png"><img src="/assets/images/darknet-credit-cards/treemap.png" alt="AlphaBay - Treemap" style="max-width: 600px" /></a></p>

<p>If you would like to check whether your credit card is in the dataset, you can either download it as a <a href="https://www.curiousgnu.com/assets/data/cc_autobuy_public.csv.gz">CSV file</a> or use the following site to search the database: <a href="https://www.curiousgnu.com/assets/tools/cc.html">www.curiousgnu.com/assets/tools/cc.html</a></p>

<h4 id="how-to-scrape-darknet-sites">How to scrape Darknet sites?</h4>

<p>Scraping <a href="https://www.torproject.org/docs/hidden-services.html.en"><em>hidden services</em></a> in the Tor network (Darknet sites) is very similar to regular web scraping with the exception that most <em>hidden services</em> don’t use JSON APIs, meaning that you have to extract the information from an HTML file. My preferred method is first to download all pages as HTML files before using Python and <em>Beautiful Soup</em> to extract the information I need. The following steps should work on OS X and Linux systems.</p>

<p><a href="/assets/images/darknet-credit-cards/alphabay_curl_web.png"><img src="/assets/images/darknet-credit-cards/alphabay_curl_web.png" alt="AlphaBay - CURL" style="max-width: 500px" /></a></p>

<ol>
  <li>Visit the site you want to scrape in the Tor Browser.</li>
  <li>Open the Web Console (<em>Right Click &gt; Inspect Element</em>).</li>
  <li>Go to the <em>Network</em> Tab.</li>
  <li>Right click on the main GET request (see Domain column) and select Copy as cURL to copy the curl command to replicate the request.</li>
  <li>Do not close the Tor browser.</li>
  <li>Before you can run the curl command in the Terminal, add the following options to the end of it <strong><em>’–socks5-hostname 127.0.0.1:9150 –output o.html’</em></strong>. It tells curl to use the Tor client and save the output to o.html.</li>
  <li>In case you want to download multiple pages, you can use the bash <em>for loop</em> like this 
<strong><em>‘for i in {1..10}; do curl […] page=${i} –output ${i}.html; done’</em></strong>.</li>
  <li>Follow the Beautiful Soup <a href="https://www.crummy.com/software/BeautifulSoup/bs4/doc/">documentation</a> to extract the need information from the saved HTML files.</li>
</ol>

<p>If you have questions or concerns, feel free to write me an <a href="&#109;&#097;&#105;&#108;&#116;&#111;:&#099;&#111;&#110;&#116;&#097;&#099;&#116;&#064;&#099;&#117;&#114;&#105;&#111;&#117;&#115;&#103;&#110;&#117;&#046;&#099;&#111;&#109;">email</a>.</p>


	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Who sells LSD on the Darktnet?</title>
	  <link>//cryptomarkets-lsd-sales</link>
	  <author>CuriousGnu</author>
	  <pubDate>2016-01-16T12:10:00+01:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//cryptomarkets-lsd-sales</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>I recently got my hands on Diana S. Dolliver’s <a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.drugpo.2015.01.008" target="_blank">paper</a> about drug dealing on the Tor network, a hidden, uncensored network which can only be accessed by <a href="https://www.torproject.org/" target="_blank">special software</a>. I got interested this topic because it allows us to analyse transactions which used to be hidden and nearly impossible to observe.</p>

<p>Besides the many legitimate use cases of the Tor network, it also provides together with Bitcoin the technology most <em>cryptomarkets</em> use. Tor allows the side administrators to host their sites anonymously without the fear of getting arrested immediately by the FBI. Cryptomarkets function similar to eBay, in the sense that they do not sell drugs directly but provide a platform where other vendors can sell their products for a small fee. The screenshot below shows how such a site looks from a buyers perspective. I chose to take a close look at the <em>AlphaBay Market</em>, one of the biggest platforms in December 2015.</p>

<p><a href="/assets/images/darknet-lsd/screenshot.png"><img src="/assets/images/darknet-lsd/screenshot.png" alt="AlphaBay Market Screenshot" title="AlphaBay Market Screenshot" /></a></p>

<h5 id="how-to-analyse-the-alphabay-market">How to analyse the AlphaBay Market?</h5>

<p>If you access one of the larger cryptomarkets, you will probably see thousands of different offerings ranging from prescription drugs to illegal weapons. The fact that anonymous users claim to sell those products, of course, does not say anything about the actual demand and volume of the sales. This is the point where it gets interesting because the <em>AlphaBay Market</em> has a revealing feedback system which lists not only lists all products sold but also their prices, and purchase dates.</p>

<p>Assuming a constant feedback ratio, we can use this data to observe the early development of the market from only one snapshot. To automatically download the customer feedbacks I wrote a scraper in Python, which provided me with the dataset for the further analysis.</p>

<h5 id="how-much-lsd-is-sold">How much LSD is sold?</h5>

<p>Unfortunately, the scraping process of a website hidden in the Tor network is a quite slow. Therefore, I decided only to download information related to LSD sales. The diagram below shows last year’s LSD sales for the weeks 13 to 50:</p>

<p><a href="/assets/images/darknet-lsd/plot_hd.png"><img src="/assets/images/darknet-lsd/plot.png" alt="LSD Sales" title="LSD Sales" /></a></p>

<p>During November 2015, approximately <strong>$215,000</strong> worth of LSD was sold on the AlphaBay Market. I do not have a definitive explanation for the sales increase following week 44, but my guess is that problems with competing cryptomarkets drove new sellers to this platform and their existing customers followed. This theory is supported by the fact that already established vendors like <em>Lyseric025</em> were not able to significantly increase their revenue during this time.</p>

<h5 id="who-are-the-dealers">Who are the dealers?</h5>

<p>To better get a better understanding of who those LSD vendors are, we need to look at their other sales also:</p>

<p><a href="/assets/images/darknet-lsd/table_hd.png"><img src="/assets/images/darknet-lsd/table.png" alt="LSD Vendors" title="LSD Vendors" /></a></p>

<p>We can see in the table above that the leading LSD seller on the AlphaBay Market was <em>Lyseric025</em>, who had a market share of 29% in November 2015 and generated a revenue of $65,438. Only 3% of it came from B2B sales (sale over $200) which suggest a strong focus on the end customer.</p>

<p>Interestingly most sellers on this list made the majority of their revenue with LSD. One of the reasons for this could be that the LSD is supposedly produced by only a <a href="http://www.justice.gov/archive/ndic/pubs25/25921/25921p.pdf" target="_blank">few producers</a> which wholesalers are probably only interested in selling in large volumes. This would mean that a specialized vendor could increase its profit by using economies of scale. I wonder if there is a similar specialization in other more decentralized drug markets.</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>


</channel>
</rss>
